<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

    <properties>
        <title>General Concepts</title>
        <author email="nospam@nowhere.edu">Kai Runte</author>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Introduction">
            <p>Each file format comes with a different set of information regarding
                a mass spectrometry experiments. The simplest ones (e.g. DTA, PKL) just
                the mass/intensity pairs for a single run, others (e.g. Sashimi) are
                quite rich in their description of a complete mass spectrometry experiment
                including not only instrument setting, but also can accommodate
                <em>all</em> of the runs done for this experiment. The M/Z data format
                is similar in complexity to the Sashimi format and requires some
                information that is not provided by the most basic formats.
            </p>
            <p>This led to the conclusion that we need a system for detecting what
                kind of information is provided by a certain format and data the
                user needs to provide. Additionally we need a flexible user
                interface that request only the information that is not provided
                by the file format and ideally displays information extracted
                from the source file format as quality assurance for the user.
            </p>
            <p>The first task (detect the file format, import it and report
                what information is missing) led to the development of the
                &quot;converter&quot; package, which is described in the
                section
                <a href="#org.psi.ms.converter">The org.psi.ms.converter Package</a>.
                The second task (provide a flexible user interface requesting the
                missing required information) led to the development of the
                &quot;view&quot; package, which is described in the
                section
                <a href="#org.psi.ms.view">The org.psi.ms.view Package</a>.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="The org.psi.ms.converter Package">
            <a name="org.psi.ms.converter"/>
            <subsection name="ImporterI">
                <p>This interface defines the functionality of an importer
                    for a certain file format. The ImporterI implementation
                    is stored in a Jar file which is loaded by the
                    <a href="#ImporterLoader">ImporterLoader class</a>.
                    In order to be accepted as a importer module each
                    converter must implement this interface and also
                    be flagged as a Bean in the Jar file it is stored in.
                    Each converter class must be able to do the following
                    things:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>initialize the conversion process by filling the Desc(ription) object.</li>
                    <li>a method "getProvidedData" returning which data the source format can
                        provide (e.g. to pre-fill fields in the GUI or to make certain other
                        field mandatory, for example the precursor for Sciex API III format)</li>
                    <li>the plugin should give feedback to the GUI in some way or another
                        (e.g. conversion process)</li>
                    <li>a method for stating whether this import module can handle files or
                        directories</li>
                    <li>a detector method simply returning true/false stating whether the
                        plugin recognises the selected data file(s)</li>
                </ul>
                <p>After initializing the application can fetch each
                    acquisition by calling the method getNextAcquisition().
                    If there are no further acquisitions, this method
                    returns null. To check for additional acquisitions
                    the methodhasMoreAcquisitions() can be called.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="ImporterLoader">
                <a name="ImporterLoader"/>
                <p>

                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="ExporterI">
                <p>This interface is for future purposes (e.g. export to
                    PRIDE or MIAPE databases) and not used yet.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
        <section name="The org.psi.ms.view Package">
            <a name="org.psi.ms.view"/>
            <p>

            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
